<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Connective Impact blog</title>
    <description>Resources and materials to guide international development nonprofits and social impact businesses in their fundraising efforts.</description>
    <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog.rss</link>
    <item>
      <title>From Crisis to Collaboration: Reimagining Global Development Beyond Traditional Aid</title>
      <description>&lt;h5&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;July 2025&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;At Connective Impact, we've spent the last few months listening deeply to what is unfolding on the ground. We&amp;rsquo;ve hosted several in-person and online meetings with funders, social enterprises, nonprofits, and frontline changemakers around the world to understand how major funding disruptions - like recent USAID cuts - have forced global development organizations to adapt. Programs have paused. Staff were sent home. Some organizations closed altogether. But the story doesn&amp;rsquo;t end there.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;In the face of this uncertainty, something remarkable has emerged. Rather than collapse under pressure, organizations, grassroots leaders, and their communities are adapting, innovating, and rising to the challenge. They are shifting from models of dependency to models of agency. We&amp;rsquo;ve heard many stories of local communities stepping up, pooling resources, volunteering, and creating innovative income-generating initiatives.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This moment is offering a powerful new vision for the future of global development - one that highlights the resilience of local actors, the rise of community agency, and the urgent need for more diversified, flexible and collaborative funding models. It&amp;rsquo;s a vision that is collaborative. Sustainable. And most importantly, led by the communities themselves.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Power of Communities Rising to the Challenge&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Too often, communities in the Global South are seen as aid recipients - but they are, in fact, leading change with agency. From raising school funds to launching enterprises, local actors are stepping up with creativity, resilience, and commitment. Amid government funding cuts and a shifting philanthropic landscape, this agency is becoming even more visible - as communities fill gaps, adapt quickly, and drive solutions from the ground up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Funders&amp;rsquo; Progress and a Vision for the Future&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Many funders are already shifting - listening more closely, easing reporting requirements, extending timelines, and investing in long-term infrastructure. Some are helping organizations cover funding gaps or transforming short-term grants into multi-year partnerships.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;But more is needed. True sustainability means funding capacity, not just programs. It means supporting income-generating assets and backing locally led innovation, even when the return on investment isn&amp;rsquo;t instant.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rethinking Funding and Partnerships for the Long-Term&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;To thrive - not just survive - organizations must explore hybrid models: blending grants, investments, and earned income. They&amp;rsquo;re also tapping into growing philanthropic capital from foundations and corporations from regions like Asia, Africa, and Latin America, and raising unrestricted funds through crowdfunding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;This is a pivotal moment. One that calls for a new kind of development: grounded in trust, built through collaboration, and led by the communities themselves.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Connective Impact&amp;rsquo;s latest breakthrough brief,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt; Reimagining Global Development&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;, surfaces trends, stories, and recommendations for funders and organizations alike. While not exhaustive, we reflect on exploratory questions like:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Are we funding for survival or sustainability?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Are we listening first, then acting?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Are we helping to build ecosystems, not just programs?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;We believe wholeheartedly that it&amp;rsquo;s time to move from crisis response to co-creation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;👉 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Fum0x9Lw3f0XhEBoPoGnoOXD6gn52t63/view" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;&lt;b&gt;Download the full PDF version of this breakthrough brief here&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; to explore and reimagine a new sector that is ready to be uncovered.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 09:43:19 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/from-crisis-to-collaboration-reimagining-global-development-beyond-traditional-aid</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/from-crisis-to-collaboration-reimagining-global-development-beyond-traditional-aid</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Proven Steps for Navigating "No Unsolicited Proposals"</title>
      <description>&lt;h3 data-pm-slice="1 1 []"&gt;How many times have you visited a funder's website only to read the dreaded "&lt;strong&gt;We Don't Accept Unsolicited Proposals&lt;/strong&gt;" language in bold letters on the home page?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p data-pm-slice="1 1 []"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What's a fundraiser to do?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p data-pm-slice="1 1 []"&gt;Hope that somehow your organization lands on their solicitation list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p data-pm-slice="1 1 []"&gt;Give up and cross the funder of your prospect list?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What's the best way to navigate this scenario?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have dealt with more of these situations than we can count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That's why we created the 4 Proven Steps guide for Navigating "No Unsolicited Proposals" from Funders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;span&gt;Now available for you in a handy step-by-step guide, you get&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;clear, actionable steps on how to navigate the "no unsolicited proposals" language, and actually build a relationship with a REAL human inside these&amp;nbsp;funder organizations that ideally lead you to the behind-the-scenes world of funding&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://s3.amazonaws.com/kajabi-storefronts-production/file-uploads/sites/47133/downloads/c7f5a80-1753-54fa-c8f2-b452c504d75_Unsolicited_Proposals_Guide.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Download the Guide HERE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 10:34:18 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/4-proven-steps-for-navigating-no-unsolicited-proposals</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/4-proven-steps-for-navigating-no-unsolicited-proposals</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2024 Leadership Transition</title>
      <description>&lt;div&gt;October 14, 2024&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Effective immediately, we are pleased to announce the transition of ownership from Joanne Sonenshine, Founder, to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://ocimpact.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Opportunity Collaboration&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;(OC) Team (currently under the leadership of &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/topherwilkins/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Topher Wilkins&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;OC has always been an important partner to us, due to the alignment of values and emphasis on utilizing collaboration and convening to solve our world&amp;rsquo;s biggest problems. Additionally, many of&amp;nbsp;our members participate in OC, so through the years we&amp;rsquo;ve listened to feedback and developed ideas internally on how to best partner with their team, so as not to duplicate our individual efforts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With the notion of jointly moving forward our respective strategies of building effective touch points, connections and ensuring the right environments for impact-led work to be funded and resourced,&amp;nbsp;we couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more pleased to announce&amp;nbsp;this transition of Connective Impact's leadership.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;OC and Connective Impact both have a deep belief in the notion of going farther together, and with such a strong overlap in mission and values, the potential to build strong growth in the &amp;ldquo;impact&amp;rdquo; ecosystem for our members, and associated partners through this transition is enormous and truly exciting.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Topher has always had a view on supporting purpose-led organizations to build stronger partnerships and connections through OC&amp;rsquo;s convenings, events and relationship building ethos. With Topher at the helm, Connective Impact will be in a stronger position to support the growth of our membership community and team, and better respond to the dynamic needs of the development and philanthropic ecosystem.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Our membership model will remain the same, and OC and Connective Impact will continue to operate as two distinct organizations. All member benefits will stay intact, and the Connective Impact brand will continue as is.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lara Berry (Membership Director) and Jinene Thompson (Membership Manager), will stay in their roles and will continue to be supported by Shelly Helgeson (Chief Strategy Officer).&amp;nbsp; Carrie Ferrence (outgoing COO) will be departing the organization after a brief transition period.&amp;nbsp;Joanne Sonenshine (Founder, outgoing CEO)&amp;nbsp;will stay on as an advisor to the OC/CI teams until March 1, 2025.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Topher will remain CEO of OC and now becomes CEO of Connective Impact. Jessica Loman, COO of OC, will take on the COO role at Connective Impact in due course.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Our teams are equally thrilled about the coming together of two purpose-oriented brands with such similar ethos and intent on creating positive change in the world through connection building and partnership.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;At the heart of Connective Impact, since&amp;nbsp;its founding&amp;nbsp;in 2014, has always been our members. We truly exist because of&amp;nbsp;them and to serve them. Thank you for the trust you have put in&amp;nbsp;us and our team over this last decade, and&amp;nbsp;we look forward to watching this organization bloom under this new leadership model.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Thank you for being a part of our journey.&lt;/div&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 10:28:23 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/2024-leadership-transition</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/2024-leadership-transition</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 Keywords That Resonate with Donors</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;There are certain keywords every funder resonates with, so when writing proposals, be sure to use one or more of these:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(1) &lt;strong&gt;Evidence-Base&lt;/strong&gt;: Emphasize how the use of data and evidence in your program design, implementation, and evaluation will be grounded in best practices and lessons learned from prior programs or pilots.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(2) &lt;strong&gt;Gender Equality and/or Social Inclusion&lt;/strong&gt;: Showcase how your programs incorporate gender equality strategies and the inclusion of marginalized or vulnerable groups.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(3) &lt;strong&gt;Localization or Local Engagement&lt;/strong&gt;: Demonstrate how your program will build upon locally-relevant knowledge, how your work will engage communities and how your work helps promote self-reliance.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(4) &lt;strong&gt;Innovation&lt;/strong&gt;: There are myriad ways to use the term innovation but if you highlight how your program is new and different, tests new approaches, tries a method that has never been tested, or is seeing results that are uncommon and set the stage for a big shift in the status quo, that's deemed innovative.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(5) &lt;strong&gt;Sustainability&lt;/strong&gt;: Highlight how your project will create lasting, sustainable impacts in the target community or region and also how funding will be matched or leveraged for the longer-term.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(6) &lt;strong&gt;Cost-Effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;: Present a well-structured budget and financial plan that demonstrates cost-effectiveness and efficiency.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(7) &lt;strong&gt;Climate&lt;/strong&gt;: If relevant, highlight how your project will address environmental sustainability and climate change resilience.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Would you add others to the list?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 12:45:32 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/DonorKeyWords</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/DonorKeyWords</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Typical Timeframe from Proposal to Funding</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;We often get asked how long fundraising will take when working with Connective Impact. While there&amp;rsquo;s no typical timeframe from making a donor connection to when funding comes in the door, I usually estimate anywhere from 6 to 18 months.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;If the fit is spot on, which is always our goal, and the donor is able to use existing budget, then funding can take as literal as a couple of months.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;For a donor that has a more intricate proposal process, and requires multiple steps for approval, it can take much longer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the lesson in thinking about timelines for funding?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Have your material ready and editable so that as we&amp;rsquo;re thinking about donor fit, and any kind of urgent timelines, we can get your material out the door as fast as possible.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;2. When developing your pipeline, rank your programs by sense of urgency. This is what we do with our &lt;a href="https://www.connectiveimpact.com/level-3-interest-form" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;Level 3&lt;/a&gt; members. We think about what funding must come in the door in the next 12 months vs what funding will help augment the growth of the organization over the next couple of years. This allows us to segment the programs we engage on now vs where we start to build a relationship for longer term funding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;3. In your prospect list, capture what is reasonable to come in the door sooner than later, and what&amp;rsquo;s more likely down the road by funder type. This keeps your projections realistic and actionable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span mce-data-marked="1"&gt;Ultimately having your priorities in order, a sense of your funding needs and the type of funder you think would be a good fit, will allow us to move as quickly as we can on our side. From there it's relying on how fast the funder will move to determine what's achievable.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 12:41:54 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/FundingTimeline</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/FundingTimeline</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 Ways to Use ChatGPT as a Fundraiser</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;What's the one thing about ChatGPT that I find problematic for fundraisers?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;ChatGPT can be a huge help to fundraisers by giving them other ways of using language in proposals, inspiring funder communication and re-stating program impact goals in multiple ways.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;t has a way of leveling the playing field, as well, making language for those that aren't native English speakers more accessible and usable in proposal development and writing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What I don't love about ChatGPT for fundraisers, is that the language still comes out very formal and "obvious." This is particularly problematic for non-native English speakers trying to write proposals in English.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But this is a real challenge in the world of authenticity and transparency in the global fundraising space.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;So how can you be using ChatGPT to help guide your fundraising process but not take it over?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Use ChatGPT for some proposal writing, but not at all. Like all of us are doing, take the output and try and augment with other tools and/or human engagement to ensure it still sounds as much like you as possible. Augmenting with Google Translate is a great addition to ensure you get your point across in language that still sounds like you.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Use ChatGPT to better understand what the donor is asking you, but then write responses in your own words, not in ChatGPTs. This way you are clearer on the approach, but still addressing proposals with language that suits you.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Ask ChatGPT several times to re-write its response using terminology that you would use. This helps the tool become more used to how you write and articulate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;And of course for funders, work on more accessible proposal methods that don't require so much English writing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;We have also prepared several ideas for using ChatGPT in your prospecting process in our FREE guide &lt;a href="https://www.connectiveimpact.com/ChatGPTProspecting" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;span class="white-space-pre"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the end, tools like ChatGPT will make the fundraising process easier for all of us. We simply must use it the right way and with the right frame of reference and it can be a game changer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 12:30:07 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/ChatGPTTips</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/ChatGPTTips</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 Biggest Tips from Donors to Doers</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There's nothing harder in fundraising than being ghosted by a funder. That, and being told that you were super close, but just not quite the best fit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, when we asked one of our donor partners what they find to be the most difficult challenges in working with doer partners, they shared that similar challenges exist for them too. Who knew both doers and donors struggle to find that perfect fit? It truly is a challenge across the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying that, below are 5 tips shared with us from donors on how to make your fundraising process more seamless:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;When asked to follow up, follow up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Don't go more than 2 weeks without returning an email.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Inform partners of leadership changes so they don't have to hear about them in the press.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;If a partner (funder or otherwise) has suggestions about how to improve the chances of working together, consider them, take them seriously and if you don't move forward with those suggestions, share why.&amp;nbsp;It's ok to be a little vulnerable. That creates trust and builds relationships&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Be honest about your funding needs. Alignment may not be perfectly there, but a funder doesn't want to be surprised by how funding is spent or not.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Working on how best to take this input and make it into something useful could be a goal for you over the next month. Let us know how it goes!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2023 12:23:44 -0700</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/DonorTips</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/DonorTips</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is It Taboo To Reach Out To Funders?</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;There was a time when it was taboo to reach out to funders.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Contact information was scarce. Intel was nonexistent. We fundraisers were playing a bit blind, save the times donors asked us to share ideas or information. It was pretty one sided.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Times have changed (a bit).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Many donors publicize their contact info. Of course many still don&amp;rsquo;t, but with an aim to shift the power, some of the larger funders recognize that contact information alone can be a game changer.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Once you have that contact info, though, what do you do with it? And what don&amp;rsquo;t you do with it?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;First, you don&amp;rsquo;t spam the funder. Don&amp;rsquo;t send anything and everything that you think they&amp;rsquo;ll be interested in.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Second, share information that you think will be valuable to them, and their work. This is a two way relationship you are trying to build, so think about any contact as an opportunity to share value and build rapport.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Third, share ideas or proposals only when the relationship gets to that level. Don&amp;rsquo;t proactively send a proposal unless you are asked.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Fourth, be considerate and respectful of peoples&amp;rsquo; time. Ask if it makes sense to have an introductory call and share ideas. Don&amp;rsquo;t ask to have a call for you to pitch. Again, this is about a relationship not a transaction.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;What else would you add to this list?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Connective Impact's Donor Outreach Blueprint covers many of these tactics. Check it out with our other &lt;a href="https://www.connectiveimpact.com/resources" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"&gt;resources&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 11:39:03 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/is-it-taboo-to-reach-out-to-funders</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/is-it-taboo-to-reach-out-to-funders</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So You Got A "No" From A Funder. Do You Remove From Your Prospect List?</title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you get a "no" from a funder, does that mean there will never be another opportunity to work with them?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Do you cross them off your prospect list all together?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Most of the time, you should keep them on the list and revisit periodically.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Why?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;1. Funder priorities shift and change as their own funding pool shifts and changes, and as their Board priorities also change based on funding interests. While alignment may not be there now, it doesn't mean it won't be there in the future. Keep an eye on how the funders' strategies are evolving and revisit when you see a better fit.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;2. Timing may be off. If the funder gives you a "not right now" that's an opportunity for you to come back to the funder at a different time of year. Funder budget cycles are based on when Board decisions are made, or when funding is allocated, so it just may be that the timing is off. Hopefully the funder will tell you that's the case, but if not, you should ask.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;3. Your own priorities may shift and change. As your organization goes through periodic program reviews, you may add or take away components of your work. As that happens, continue to evaluate whether your new strategies are better aligned with the funder before going back again and inquiring as such.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;4. Geographic needs may change along with programmatic needs, both on your side and the funder's. It's a good idea to check in with funders regularly (no less than once a quarter) to see how this may be the case. Once there's alignment it's a much easier case to make that the two of you should be working together.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;As always, keep an eye on your prospect list and refine as you go through your prospecting process.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;How do you regularly evaluate whether a "no" is a "not now" or "not ever?"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 11:33:29 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/so-you-got-a-no-from-a-funder-do-you-remove-from-your-prospect-list</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/so-you-got-a-no-from-a-funder-do-you-remove-from-your-prospect-list</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 4 Different Types of International Development Funding </title>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;As you seek institutional funding for your work around international development, there are four buckets of funding you should be considering. Having a strategy for each will be game-changing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;These four buckets are:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Government/Public&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Foundation/Philanthropic&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Corporate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Impact Investor-Led (depending on your business model)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Each type of funder has its own unique requirements and preferences, so it's important to research and target the right funders for your organization's needs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Let's start with &lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;Government/Public&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Government grants (like from USAID or the EU) or funding from public development agencies like the IDB, GEF or GCF can be a good source of funding for organizations that align with government priorities and objectives AND that are able to receive large sums of money.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The proposal development process for government grants can be complex and time-consuming. There are exceptions, of course, so it's worth diving into this bucket to see where you best fit. Additionally, piggy-backing off a partner that has relationships with government funders is a great way to learn about requirements, opportunities, and how to position your organization to receive these larger tranches of funding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Keep an eye on LinkedIn pages like WorkWithUSAID and consider where your partnerships can help you get more involved in government funded programs. Be prepared to educate yourself on process, rules, and regulations if you don't already know them.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The payoff can be high, but restriction can also be high (i.e. government funders are NOT the ones to look to for unrestricted, flexible funding).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Next is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;Foundation/Philanthropic&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Private foundation grants, compared to government funds, are more flexible and accessible. They aren't always unrestricted, but requirements are often less onerous.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Foundations often lay out priorities for their giving, with specific areas of focus or geographic restrictions. We always advise our members to study the foundation's website thoroughly to identify the best potential alignment before applying for a foundation grant. The Venn diagram of priorities must be pretty large for you to be a consideration.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Funding levels can be in the multi-million dollar range (and increasingly so with the trends towards big bets) but on average tend to be in the low six figures. Foundation grants are a great opportunity to test out a new program, pilot test a new idea, or help add resources to a program that needs a refresh.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Government grants budgets are detailed and reviewed with a fine-tooth comb; for foundation grants you will need a strong budget that can be easily explained. But priorities are around realistic, transparent, and aligned priorities.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;For funders that don't accept unsolicited proposals, utilize our &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://connectiveimpact.gumroad.com/l/Guide?_gl=1*ta5ipn*_ga*MTQ5ODI0NjUyMS4xNjU4NjgwOTY1*_ga_6LJN6D94N6*MTY1OTQ1OTA0My4xMC4xLjE2NTk0NTkwNDQuMA.."&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;4 Step Guide &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;to help you navigate this path. There are ways to be seen, and having a facilitated intro is often a great way to get more information on whether you have alignment or not.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;If questioning whether to submit a concept note, or letter of inquiry to a foundation, ask yourself first whether you see complete alignment of mission and ideas. If the answer is yes, do send, and see how we can help you move that concept to proposal with the right intro. This is a people business in the end, especially for foundations/philanthropies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Corporate&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Corporate funding can come in many forms to nonprofits, although most organizations look for CSR or cause marketing as a way to augment unrestricted funds. Some also look for employee engagement funding.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Instead of seeing the philanthropic dollars as the way in, try and understand a corporate&amp;rsquo;s business model. Where do they source product from? Where are their operations? What are their impact goals? Do they have an interesting program underway in a geography where you also work that supports local communities? Is there a way your work would help support a tenant of a corporate&amp;rsquo;s investment strategy in the Global South?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;You want to see corporates as collaborators &amp;mdash; and understand how their investment in themes or geographies match yours. How can your efforts help the corporate improve their business model, work better in regions where they are operating, source more efficiently or provide more opportunities for its workforce, communities or broader network? CSR and how a business functions are essentially one and the same these days (hallelujah!).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Consider how an outside investment from a corporate can augment an existing funded program you have, and approach the corporate as a leverage partner&amp;mdash;not just for a donation.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Corporate funding can be a great unrestricted, flexible funding source, but it takes a good amount of patience, due diligence, and consideration to find the right match for your work.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;The last category of funding is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;impact investment funding&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; (or funding that is invested in an enterprise with the expectation of a financial return on that investment).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Impact investment capital is used by an investor looking to make money off of his/her investment in an organization that is designed to deliver a product or service for a profit of some sort. While impact investors can work with nonprofits, they can do so only if the program they are investing in has some sort of financial churn. This is obviously quite different from a funder that is just investing for a social or environmental outcome.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Most impact investors investing in the Global South do seek to improve on a social or environmental outcome, but seeing a financial return is a priority.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Why? Because investors are priming the development landscape to be more market-driven and to incentivize an economic system that is driven by business creation, not pure philanthropy. The expectation is that these enterprises, when funded properly, can help support local development for the longer term and be self-sustaining, create jobs, and strengthen a local system better than philanthropy can.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Some impact investors will provide venture philanthropy, which is grant funding followed by debt or equity. Others may invest with forgivable debt (i.e. it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be repaid). But most do invest with traditional or blended finance tools like loans, equity, and other forms of debt.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Investments can be small or large depending on the recipient.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;As you evolve your fundraising strategy, understanding the full funding landscape gives you a much more focused approach to considering which funders and funder types are most likely to support your organization's work so you can target them effectively. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.connectiveimpact.com/"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt;Ask us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: 400;"&gt; how we can help you engage funders for a more effective outcome!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 05:45:03 -0600</pubDate>
      <link>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/different-types-of-funding</link>
      <guid>https://www.connectiveimpact.com/blog/different-types-of-funding</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
